Guide to the Frank Kellogg Smith Travel Photographs and Memorabilia
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frank Kellogg Smith travel photographs and memorabilia.
1898-1959
1898-1922
GEN MSS 567
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3
(20 boxes) + 2 broadside folders
The collection consists of photograph albums, loose photographs, and memorabilia compiled by Frank Kellogg Smith that document his travels, predominately in western and central Europe, southern and eastern Africa, and the southern Pacific region, primarily from 1898-1922. Locations in Europe include Azerbaijan, Belgium, Channel Islands, France, Georgia, Great Britain (consisting of trips to England and Scotland), Hungary, Malta, Netherlands, Romania, Russia, Switzerland, and Ukraine. Locations in Africa include Egypt, Kenya, Madeira Islands, Mozambique, Rhodesia (Zambia and Zimbabwe), Somalia, South Africa, Tanzania, Uganda, Yemen, and Zanzibar, as well as Victoria Falls and the Nile River. Locations in the Pacific include Australia, Canada, Fiji, Hawaii, New Zealand, Samoa, and the United States of America, which consist of views in Arizona, California, and New Mexico.
Smith, Frank Kellogg, 1873-1968
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Bonnie F. Young and A David Young, Jr., 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biography of Frank Kellogg Smith
Frank Kellogg Smith was born in Elizabeth, New Jersey, on April 15, 1873. His parents were Walter O. Smith (b. 1843) and Henrietta "Nettie" Wells Smith (b. 1848). In 1900 he was employed as a clerk, but by 1911 he was the representative for the United States Steel Corporation in South Africa. Smith later worked for the Standard Oil Company of New York. His residences in the United States included homes in Bronxville and New York City, New York, and Ivoryton, Connecticut. Smith married Isabelle Cleveland Kelsey on July 11, 1911; she died on February 12, 1943, in Ivoryton, Connecticut. He then married Sarah Anneke Van Ellendorf Lancraft on August 24, 1965. Smith was a member and president of the Circumnavigators Club, an organization devoted to bringing together those men and women who have circumnavigated the globe. Smith died in November 1968.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of photograph albums, loose photographs, and memorabilia compiled by Frank Kellogg Smith of his travels, predominately in western and central Europe, southern and eastern Africa, and the southern Pacific region, primarily from 1898-1922, with additional materials to circa 1889-1959. Strengths of the collection include photographic documentation at the turn of the twentieth century of localities and peoples in southern and eastern Africa, as well as southeastern Europe.
Titles to the albums come from imprinted titles or manuscript inscriptions by Smith.
Several images are duplicated in photographic prints in different albums, especially those albums documenting trips in Africa. Albums in boxes 14-18 primarily possess photographic prints that duplicate images in the albums in boxes 1-13.
Many of the photographic prints are accompanied by manuscript captions in the negative or in the albums.
Arrangement
Photograph albums in the collection are arranged chronologically, followed by loose photographic materials, which includes photographs by Smith and others, and then by memorabilia, which includes artwork, maps, papers, and then by oversize materials.
Voyages and travels -- Pictorial works; Africa -- Pictorial works; Australia -- Pictorial works; Europe -- Pictorial works; New Zealand -- Pictorial works; Pacific Area -- Pictorial works; United States -- Pictorial works; Photograph albums; Photographic prints; Smith, Frank Kellogg, 1873-1968; Circumnavigators' Club (New York, N.Y.); Socony-Vacuum Oil Company -- Employees; United States Steel Corporation -- Employees
- Photograph Albums, Series I
  General note
  18 albums containing 4247 photographic prints
  Arrangement
  Albums arranged roughly chronologically. Most photographic prints mounted in the albums possess captions in the negatives or manuscript captions on the leaves.
  - Scotland, Holland, Belgium, France, Switzerland, 1898-1902, 1907; (Leatherbound album, 28.2 X 41.0 cm, containing 147 photographic prints) (Box 1)
    Photographic prints mounted in the album. Many of the photographic prints have captions in the negatives.
    Scope and Contents
    This album contains photographs that document excursions in France and Scotland in June-July 1898; England, Belgium, France, and Switzerland, in July-September 1899; the Exposition Universelle in Paris, France, in June 1900; Switzerland in November 1900; the Netherlands in June 1901; Belgium in August 1902; and France in June 1907.
    Images of particular interest include an informal portrait of King Oscar II of Sweden in Paris in June-July 1898, as well as informal portraits of Frederick VIII of Denmark, Émile François Loubet, and Georges Clemenceau, in June 1907.
  - New Zealand - England, 1898-circa 1900; (Leatherbound album, 28.2 X 41.0 cm, containing 217 photographic prints) (Box 2)
    Many of the photographic prints documenting the trip to New Zealand are missing from the album pages, and are in Box 19, folder 9.
    This album contains photographs from an excursion in New Zealand, ca. 1900, and excursions in England, April-June 1898, September-October 1898, May 1899, and September 1899. Many of the photographic prints documenting the trip to New Zealand are missing from the album pages. There are also several views of Sark, Channel Islands.
    Images of particular interest include views of Richmond, England, which includes views of a horse show and the vicinity.
  - Italy, Roumania (sic.), Russia, 1900, 1907; (Leatherbound album, 28.2 X 41.0 cm, containing 151 photographic prints) (Box 3)
    This album contains photographs from two excursions; one excursion that included Hungary, Romania, Ukraine, Georgia, Russia, and Azerbaijan, March 1900-September 1900; the other excursion included Italy and the Vatican City, May1907-June 1907.
    Images of particular interest document petroleum extraction in the localities of Gura Ocniţei and Târgovişte, Romania, and in Baku and Balachany, Azerbaijan.
  - South Africa, 1903-1904, 1910-1911; (Leatherbound album, 28.2 X 41.0 cm, containing 272 photographic prints) (Box 4)
    This album contains photographs from excursions in South Africa from disparate dates including January 1903, August 1904, September to October 1910, August 1911, and February 1912. Several photographs include informal portraits of white and black Africans, including images of latter individuals performing native dances. Several incidental images show views of streets of Funchal, Madeira Island, in August 1902, September 1910, and August 1911.
  - South Africa - Transvaal, 1903-1906, no date; (Leatherbound album, 28.2 X 41.0 cm, containing 220 photographic prints) (Box 5)
    This album contains photographs that document excursions in South Africa in March-April 1903 and August 1906, as well as an undated excursion.
    Several photographs include informal portraits of white and black Africans, including images of latter individuals performing native dances, as well as several images of Chinese immigrants.
  - Rhodesia, East Africa, Egypt, 1906, 1907, 1910; (Leatherbound album, 28.2 X 41.0 cm, containing 279 photographic prints) (Box 6)
    This album contains photographs from three excursions; the first excursion journeyed from South Africa into Rhodesia (Zambia and Zimbabwe), May 1906; the second excursion journeyed from Mozambique, through Zanzibar, Kenya, and Yemen, April 1907 to May 1907, and the third from Kenya to Uganda, December 1910. Several photographs include informal portraits of white and black Africans, including images of latter individuals performing native dances.
  - African Photographs [I], 1910; (Clothbound album, 24.8 X 36.3 cm, containing 354 photographic prints) (Box 7)
    This album contains photographs that document excursions to and in Africa, including South Africa, Rhodesia (Zambia and Zimbabwe), Mozambique, Tanzania, and Zanzibar, circa Sep-Dec 1910. The album probably documents a trip by Smith and his first wife, Isabelle Kelsey, prior to their marriage. The album also includes maps of Africa and Victoria Falls. Many of the photographic prints are also hand-colored.
  - African Photographs [II], 1910; (Clothbound album, 24.8 X 36.3 cm, containing 420 photographic prints) (Box 8)
    This album contains photographs that document excursions to and in Africa, including South Africa, Rhodesia (Zambia and Zimbabwe), Mozambique, Tanzania, Zanzibar, Kenya, Yemen, Somalia, Egypt, Malta, France, England, and the United States, circa Sep-Dec 1910. The album probably documents a trip by Smith and his first wife, Isabelle Kelsey, prior to their marriage. The album also includes maps of Africa, Victoria Falls, and the Nile River. Many of the photographic prints are also hand-colored.
  - African Photographs [III], 1910; (Clothbound album, 24.8 X 36.3 cm, containing 358 photographic prints) (Box 9)
    This album contains photographs that document excursions in Africa including locations in Zanzibar, Kenya, Uganda, and Egypt, circa Sep-Dec 1910. The album probably documents a trip by Smith and his first wife, Isabelle Kelsey, prior to their marriage. The album also includes a map of Africa. Many of the photographic prints are also hand-colored.
  - African Photographs [IV], 1910; (Clothbound album, 24.8 X 36.3 cm, containing 401 photographic prints) (Box 10)
    This album contains photographs that document excursions to and in Africa, including Egypt, Malta, England, South Africa, Mozambique, Zanzibar, Kenya, and the Madeira Islands, circa Sep-Dec 1910. The album probably documents a trip by Smith and his first wife, Isabelle Kelsey, prior to their marriage. The album also includes two maps of the Nile River. Many of the photographic prints are also hand-colored.
  - Australia, 1912-1916; (Leatherbound album, 28.2 X 41.0 cm, containing 274 photographic prints) (Box 11)
    This album contains photographs that document excursions in Australia in April 1912, September 1912-January 1913, March 1913, December 1914, May 1915, August 1915, and March 1916. Many photographic prints are loose in the album. Several images include views of sunbathers in water and shoreline. There are also images of wildlife including koala bears and a Kookaburra birds.
  - Pacific, 1912-1913; (Clothbound album, 24.8 X 36.3 cm, containing 367 photographic prints) (Box 12)
    This album contains photographs that document excursions in the Pacific region, including Canada, Fiji, Australia, American Samoa, Hawaii, California, Arizona, and New Mexico, November 1912-March 1913. Many of the photographic prints are also hand-colored.
  - South Pacific, United States, North Atlantic, 1913-1914, 1916, 1919-1920, 1922; (Leatherbound album, 28.2 X 41.0 cm, containing 276 photographic prints) (Box 13)
    This album contains photographs that document excursions in Vermont in September 1913; California and New Mexico in January 1914; California and Arizona in May 1916; New York in September 1919; New York in February 1920; and Virginia and Washington, D.C., in April 1922, as well as undated locations in Connecticut, Hawaii, and Samoa.
  - [Tan Album], 1897-1898; (Cloth-bound album, 26.1 X 20.8 cm, containing 144 photographic prints) (Box 14)
    This album contains photographs of trips to England in May-June 1897, October 1897, and April 1898, including an excursion to the Channel Islands, as well as photographs from undated excursions to France. There are also incidental undated images of Scotland.
  - [Red No. 1], 1898; (Cloth-bound album, 26.1 X 20.8 cm, containing 96 photographic prints) (Box 15)
    This album contains photographs that document numerous excursions including England in April-June 1898, and France and Scotland in June-July 1898.
  - [Red No. 2], 1898-1900, 1902; (Cloth-bound album, 26.1 X 20.8 cm, containing 78 photographic prints) (Box 16)
    This album contains photographs that document locations primarily in England, September-October 1898, May-September 1899, and April 1900, as well as incidental images of Ukraine in April 1900, France in June 1900, Belgium in August and December 1900, and the Funchal, Madeira Island in August 1902.
  - [Maroon No. 1], 1899-1900; (Leather-bound album, 26.1 X 20.8 cm, containing 95 photographic prints) (Box 17)
    This album contains photographs that document numerous excursions including: France and Switzerland in July-September 1899; Georgia in March 1900; Hungary, Romania, Ukraine, and Switzerland in September to November 1900; and undated discrete views of Chamonix-Mont-Blanc, France, and the Caucasus Mountain region.
  - [Maroon No. 2], 1900-1902, 1904; (Leather-bound album, 26.1 X 20.8 cm, containing 98 photographic prints) (Box 18)
    This album contains photographs that document numerous excursions including: Ukraine, Russia, and Azerbaijan, April 1900; Netherlands and Belgium, June-July 1901; Netherlands, July-August 1902; and South Africa, June-August 1904.
- Loose Photographic Materials, circa 1900-1913; Series II; (114 photographic prints)
  Photographic prints are arranged alphabetically by geographic location.
  Loose photographic prints created by Frank Kellogg Smith that accompanied the photograph albums.
  Each folder contains a single photographic print, except where two or more photographic prints are noted.
  - Photographic Prints Created by Smith
    - Australia, 1913 Jan; (12 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 1)
      Panoramic views of Manly Beach, Sydney
    - Egypt, Heliopolis, 1907 May 23 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - France, Mont Blanc, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Great Britain, London, residence in Herne Hill (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Hawaii, Oahu, children at the mission of St. Mary's Episcopal Church, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - India, including Agra, Delhi, and Kolkata, (5 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Italy, Capri, 1907 Jun 1 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Netherlands, Scheveningen promenade, 1902 Apr 1 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - New Zealand, circa 1900; (42 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 9)
      Images of Auckland, Christchurch, Lake Wakatipu, Rangitoto Island, River Avon, Rotorua, Waimangu Geyser, and Wanganui
      Photographic prints formerly in "New Zealand - England" album
    - South Africa, 1904, Aug 9, and 1928, Feb 26; (8 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 10)
      Informal portraits of Zulu women washing clothes in the Amanzimtoti River, a view of the Johannesburg Country Club, and informal portraits of Zulu women and men dancing
    - United States of America, Palm Beach, Florida, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Victoria Falls, n.d.; (14 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Yemen, Aden, n.d.; (7 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Zanzibar, 1907, May 5; (4 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 14)
      Informal portraits of Prince Albrecht of Prussia and views of Black Africans
    - Unidentified Locations in Africa, n.d.; (5 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 15)
      Informal portraits of Frank Kellogg Smith, as well as informal portraits of Black Africans
    - Unidentified locations, n.d.; (10 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 16)
      Includes a view of the SS Kaiser Wilhelm der Große
  - Photographic Negatives by Smith, 1904
    - Special Africa Pictures, 1904, Jul-Aug; (20 black and white film negatives) (Box 19, Folder 17)
      Informal portraits of Black Africans
  - Collected Photographs, circa 1889- circa 1940; (51 photographic prints)
    Arranged alphabetically by surname of photographer or name of photography studio.
    Photographic prints collected by Smith from professional and amateur photographers and photographic studios.
    - Barnett Isaacs, Joseph, (circa 1861-1897) and David Isaacs, circa 1889-1900; Identified by stamps on verso, "J. and D. Barnett"; (17 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 18)
      Biographical/Historical note
      Studio located in Johannesburg, South Africa
      Informal and studio portraits of Black Africans, including Ndebele people and Zulu people, as well as a Black African family in the Murchison Range of mountains
    - Binks, Herbert K. "Pop" (circa 1880-1971), circa 1900-1915; (13 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 19)
      Studio located in Nairobi, Kenya
      Images include views of Black Africans, including Kamba and Kĩkũyũ people
    - Clark, Percy M. (1874-1937), circa 1905; (1 photographic print) (Box 19, Folder 20)
      Studio located in Victoria Falls
      Group portrait of fifty-two White African children, women, and men
    - Coutinho and Sons, circa 1900; (5 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 21)
      Studio located in Mombasa, Kenya
      Probably D. Evaristo Coutinho and his sons
    - De Lord Brothers, A. R. Pereira de Lord and Kampuni de Lord, circa 1900; (1 photographic print) (Box 19, Folder 22)
      Studio located in Zanzibar
      Studio portrait of five Black African girls, probably Swahili girls
    - Moiton, (Miss), circa 1932; (1 photographic print) (Box 19, Folder 23)
      View of Palm Grove, Victoria Falls
    - Pedrotti, L., circa 1902; (2 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 24)
      Studio located in Bulawayo, Zimbabwe
      Views of Victoria Falls and of World's View, Matobo Hills, Zimbabwe
    - Smart & Copley, n.d.; (4 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 25)
      Pharmacy firm located in Bulawayo, Zimbabwe
      Views of Victoria Falls, the Victoria Falls bridge, and of Bulawayo, Zimbabwe.
    - Unidentified Photographer, n.d.; (4 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 26)
      Informal portraits of Black African, including Kavirondo people
    - Unidentified Photographer, n.d.; (1 photographic print) (Box 19, Folder 27)
      Interior portrait of an unidentified large group of women and men
    - Unidentified Photographers, circa 1920, circa 1940; (2 photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 28)
      Portraits of Frank Kellogg Smith
- Memorabilia, Series III
  - Artwork
    - "A Corner of Moçambique", 1910, Dec (Box 19, Folder 29)
      Watercolor painting by an unidentified artist depicts sailing ships by a shore with buildings
  - Maps
    - Railways in Southeastern Africa, 1909-1910 (Box 19, Folder 30)
      Railways include Beira Railway, Mashonaland Railway, Rhodesia Katanga Junction Railway, and Rhodesia Railways Limited
      Telegraph lines documented include the African Transcontinental Telegraph
    - Victoria Falls of the Zambezi River, circa 1910 (Box 19, Folder 31)
      Handdrawn map includes locations of a railroad, ferry routes, canoe paths, and footpaths
  - Ephemera
    - Brochures for Herbert Penny (Pty.) Ltd., South Africa, 1958, Jan-Dec (Box 19, Folder 32)
      Regarding real estate in Cape Town, South Africa
    - Program for a dinner commemorating the third anniversary of the People-to-People Program, 1959, Sep 30 (Box 19, Folder 33)
    - Typescript description of fabrication of tapa cloth in Polynesia, with particular emphasis on Tahiti, no date (Box 19, Folder 34)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Steamer Clement Hill on Lake Victoria, circa 1932 (Box 19, Folder 35)
    - "Yeta Waves Fly Switch", 1937, May 4 (Box 19, Folder 36)
      About the attendance of Mulena Yomuhulu Mbumu wa Litunga Yeta III, Litunga of the Lozi and Paramount Chief of Borotseland, at the coronation of George VI
    - "Sightseeing, but Not for Pleasure," New York Herald Tribune, 1943, Oct 22 (Box 19, Folder 37)
      View of a United States Army Air Transport Command plane over the Pyramids of Egypt
    - Magazine clipping, probably from National Geographic Magazine of a tree in autumn, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 38)
- Oversize Materials, circa 1923- circa 1940; Series IV
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - Rotogravure Picture section of the New York Times about the Valley of the Kings, Egypt, 1923, Mar 11 (Box 20, Folder 39)
  - Photographic Prints
    - Group Portraits, circa 1930-1940 (Box 20, Folder 40-41)
  - Ephemera, circa 1935
    - Menu for the Canada Steamship Lines, circa 1935 (Box 20, Folder 42)
  - Maps
    - John Bartholomew & Co., Bartholomew's reduced survey map of South Africa: coloured to show height of land (Edinburgh, Scotland: Edinburgh Geographical Institute), circa 1900-1910; 1 map: color, mounted on linen, 63.0 x 86.8 cm. (Box Bsd, folder 43)
    - John Bartholomew and Son, Map of Central and South Africa (Edinburgh, Scotland: John Bartholomew & Son), circa 1900-1910; 1 map: color, mounted on linen, 99 x 81 cm. (Box Bsd, folder 44)